start. Um please the reminder that I
give in most of the meetings or is
whenever I remember but most of the
meetings is that because we are
recording and so that we can ensure that
this goes out to the public please watch
your language make sure that language is
appropriate. Um it is also one of the
two reasons why we do not have everybody
on visual uh for their uh for their
faces to show and that is just to ensure
that in the background there is not
something inappropriate that we would
then later have to delete out or
potentially not be able to show the
video and have it as part of the public
record. And so, um, with that in mind,
my name is Dominic Zerlo with the
Department of Health and, uh, this is
the patient qualification and safety
committee with the chair, Ian Dunn. And
so, um, Ian, I will turn it on over to
you. All righty. Well, thank you,
Dominic. Good morning, everyone. I'm
going to call the patient qualification
and safety committee to order. My name
is Ian Dunn. I'm the chair of this
committee. Thank you all for being here.
I really appreciate all of your input
and working on this project together. Um
before we begin, just a reminder, we are
an advisory committee. Our role is to
think carefully, stress test ideas, and
forward recommendations to the board. Uh
next slide.
Perfect. So, what we're going to be
going over today is a clinical support
framework, um, which is going to allow
us to
put patients into areas where they will
receive the support that they need if
they are going to go through the medical
psilocybin program. Um, we also discuss
a few program exclusions. They're mostly
mirrored off of Oregon, um, and what
they exclude. And then we can discuss
certain psycho psychiatric and
neurological conditions um in order for
placement in that support tier. See how
much support they need versus are they
just a standard protocol and additional
support is not required at this time. If
we can go to slide three.
Quick reminder, committees operate in
advisory capacity. They provide forum
for individuals who may be experts but
may not serve on the board due to real
or perceived conflicts of interest.
Committees support the board by
expanding comm community input,
incorporating subject matter expertise,
and increasing participation in program
development. Next slide.
All right. So now we can go ahead and
look at the actual clinical support
tiers.
So the clinical support tier framework
that I had uh created has four tiers.
There is tier one which is going to be
standard eligibility. They have no
additional requirements or other um
necessary support for them to be in the
program. Tier 2 is an enhanced support
mechanism.
Tier three is a specialist supported um
and tier four is not appropriate at this
time. We can't provide enough clinical
support in order for this to be
appropriate. So the goal of this
document is not to exclude unnecessar
unnecessarily. The goal is to calibrate
support to risk. So before we get into
specifics, um I did want to ask does
anyone have any um highle concerns about
the structure itself? Um while we work
on getting that pulled up to be a little
bit bigger for everyone in um the chat
to see, we can look at the structure
itself.
>> One second.
Uh there's a request in the chat if fake
uh what was on the screen can be uh
pasted into the chat and made larger to
see please.
>> All right. And while we're working on
making it a little bit bigger, I have
gone ahead and posted the um text of the
document in the chat. So that way if you
guys are able to pull that up, it might
be a little bit easier to read. I know
sometimes when we're sharing our
screens, it can get a little blurred. Um
so that option is there. I will once
again say um are there any highle
concerns about the structure itself? I
will give you guys a little bit to
review. Um
yeah.
This is Larry Leman. Can you hear me?
>> Yes sir.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, so one question I have there when it
says standard support proceed with the
standard protocol. Have we been provided
with the standard protocol or is that
something that's in development?
>> That is also um in development. is going
to be the um for us to end up deciding.
The reason I wanted to put a little bit
of exclusion or extra support criteria
first was that way it would allow us to
say okay for the standard protocol we
know that all of these um conditions
that may cause complexities are going to
have their own clinical support. That
way we can make the standard as
streamlined as possible.
Okay, thank you. Ian, does that mean the
standard protocol will have a
requirement for a medical personnel to
have indicated that they have one of the
four conditions?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. Will they be required to see the
patient as a
so right now um we have not come up with
any exclusion to the fact that they
would have to see a provider. I know
that the equity and cultural
considerations committee had talked
about tellahalth for certain aspects of
it. However, um for the specific
situation in which a provider authorizes
the use of psilocybin, um I don't have
that specific framework produced.
Ian, we have uh an Mets with her hand
raised. An I've uh enabled your
microphone credentials. Whenever you're
ready, you may unmute yourself.
>> Great. Thank you so much. Um Ian, this
looks wonderful. Um you know, one thing
that does come to mind between tier 2
and tier three,
um you know, tier three makes a lot of
sense if the facilitator doesn't have um
an independent license in behavioral
health or in medicine. Um, and so I'm
thinking that, you know, I practice in
Colorado and uh as a clinical
facilitator and I'm able to see people
with risk, high-risisk conditions on my
own. And so, um, I wonder if there's
something between enhanced clinical
support and having to have two
clinicians present if the facilitator
has a secondary license that allows them
to diagnose, assess, and treat
behavioral health conditions
on their own.
>> Yeah. Um, I would concur with that. The
reason I had separated them is because a
lot of times um
providers will start to work within just
one program. So sometimes they'll kind
of put some focus on maybe they want to
be a medical psilocybin doctor and they
want that's the medicine that they
believe in. It was to provide an avenue
for that. But I definitely understand
where you're coming from and could see a
situation where yeah like if you're um a
licensed psychiatrist should you have to
also get a primary psilocybin
practitioner. So um if that is a change
um that you would like to make we could
say um that there's just a specialist
involved not two signitories a
specialist and a um
psilocybin provider. Is that what you
were getting at?
>> Yeah, I think for tier three for
instance, so if somebody is dually
licensed as a facilitator and also has a
behavioral health license, if they're a
social worker or they're a counselor, um
you know, I think in that instance, they
don't necessarily need to have a second
person present because their secondary
license would cover the basically the
second person.
>> Okay. Yeah. Um, I appreciate that
comment. I will definitely I do want to
hear from some other people, but I
definitely could see that being logical
and reasonable.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. Next up, Ian, uh, we have
Alan with her hand raised. Alan, I've
enabled your microphone credentials.
Whenever you're ready, you can unmute
yourself.
>> Hi, thank you. Um, I was wondering there
was another document sent out this
morning that was the it was a two-page
document with the qualifying conditions
clinical warning. Is is that the same
four tiers that we're talking about here
or is that something different? So that
document was more so a kind of rough
draft of what this tier system would
look like in if we fully flushed it out
if we did all of the steps to work on
it. Not saying that I created a perfect
document. That is not it. I just wanted
to show a visual example of what these
four tiers looked like in practice.
>> Okay. Thanks. because I know in the
specialist review, similar to the last
comment, um it very specifically states
that a psychiatrist needs to be
involved, but I would argue that other
mental health providers who are licensed
um independently credentialed in the
state, including psychiatric mental
health nurse practitioners who can
assess and diagnose um would be
appropriate in that third tier as well.
Thank you.
>> I concur. Thank you.
Next up is Katherine. Katherine, I've
enabled your microphone credentials.
Whenever you're ready, you can unmute
yourself.
>> Good morning. Um, I think just based on
um the the document that was sent out
this morning and being able to see a
little bit more what the tiers are
supposed to include, I actually think
tier three would be good if we had two
people. It doesn't necessarily have to
be um you know I mean I don't know what
levels of those like what their
backgrounds are but I don't know I think
for tier three based on what was listed
in there they are conditions that I
don't know as a facilitator I think I
would want backup. I would want to make
sure that I consulted with somebody else
and that both people are agreeing to
move forward. Um I just think that's a I
don't know that's that's my opinion. I
think that's not a bad thing to include.
So,
>> yeah, I really appreciate that. Um, so
when I had done it, I had it was quasi a
red, yellow, green light, um, with two
yellow steps. The tier 2 was supposed to
be like, hey, here's a here's a warning.
Like, it may not be that big of a deal.
It may end up, you know, not having as
many consequences. And then tier three
was um disorders where we could have um
psychosis or other things of that
nature. So I definitely did in my
intention make it have two providers
because a it distributes the liability
on those providers allowing them to say
well I took every step necessary to
ensure that there was proper patient
care including consulting with a
professional. So I do um I do agree in
part with that but I could also
understand you know saying well if the
facilitator is also a licensed um
clinical counselor then maybe they could
also be a signatory on that. Um but I do
like
>> I also think I'm sorry to interrupt but
I was also going to say maybe we make it
optional. Like for example um I can't
remember the the woman that just spoke
about it. If she's confident and
comfortable with just being both roles,
then okay. But like I guess for me, I
would want to have a second opinion um
because of the severity and the
liability. So
>> I appreciate your comment.
>> Thank you. And uh before I proceed to
Lisa, I just want to address in the chat
real briefly. and Mets asked if it was
possible to get a copy of what was sent
out this morning. Uh it looks like Ellen
Shimls posted some screenshots. Thank
you for that. Um Dr. Lida uh concurs and
then uh Alan also confirms that what was
sent out this morning. And then next I'm
going to go ahead and enable the
microphone credentials of Lisa. Whenever
you're ready, go ahead and unmute
yourself.
All right, Lisa, your microphone has
been enabled. Just as a friendly
reminder, if you're on the Teams app,
it's the microphone icon.
Uh, if there's any technical issues, you
should.
>> Yeah, perfect.
>> Uh, hi. Sorry. Yes, I had a technical
issue. Uh, hi, my name is Lisa Ginsburg.
I'm the founder of Sha Institute. So uh
thank you so much for putting this great
document. I have few um
um a few pieces of information that I
wanted to share. Uh first for um
specialist review requirements. I think
it's important to uh be clear and create
a definition of which specialist is
required to sign a specific condition or
form. Can a can nurse practitioner
qualify for a specialist to assess
eating disorders and mental health
conditions including also heart
conditions or would you require a
specific specialist assign on specific
conditions? Um, and I'm simply saying it
because I remember the days back um
years ago in California when you would
walk on Venice Beach and there would be
would prescribe um medical marijuana for
$20 to pretty much anyone. You would
just go in the shop and say no more. I
know you need this prescription and uh
we want to make sure that this uh rules
would not allow such practice. Um the
second uh comment I have is in terms of
the second practitioner uh this can uh
turn the sessions quite expensive
especially if insurance is not covering
that. Uh also if you are planning to
include second practitioner in the
session um
to have training license with
facilitation because just uh just
because someone is licensed in uh
psychiatry or psychology or some other
conditions doesn't mean that they know
how to co- facilitate psychedelic
sessions. So um with that I would
encourage to require a license for the
second practitioner and people were
involved in the session as well. Um
thank you.
>> Thank you for that Lisa.
So next up with their hand raises Hannah
Rose. Hannah your microphone has been
enabled. Whenever you're ready go ahead
and unmute yourself.
Anna, your mic.
>> Hi. Thank you. Sorry. Thank you. Thanks
for your patience.
>> Oh, good morning. So nice to see you all
again and really lovely to hear from
everyone. My name is Hana Rose. I am a
BW student and a first generation
Kurandera. Um, so my question
>> is that
>> is
>> um on the
>> third tier. Can can we scroll down to
the third tier there?
>> Oh, good.
>> Okay.
>> So, my question is like a Can you guys
be a little quieter? Thank you. Um
um for the de the DEI considerations,
the diversity, equity, and inclusion
considerations.
Um how where where do like third gen
like New Mexican coderas like fit into
this consideration
here on tier number three?
>> Can you speak to that please?
So specifically I can't in this
committee that would fall under the
training and education committee who
sets the lensure requirements for um
practitioners as well as for um
the facilitator.
So personally this committee isn't going
to be in the jurisdiction of that. So I
can't speak to
>> Okay. So then so then my question my
next question is um
Let's see. Primary psilocyb
practitioner. I guess I guess my I'm
just wondering um
>> I guess I just want to um kind of um
agree with the last woman that spoke
that
>> Yeah, I just want to agree and just kind
of reinforce what she said. Um, and
thank you for for, you know, keeping us
all in our lanes here with the proper
committees and um, yeah, that's all for
now. Thanks.
>> No worries. Thank you so much.
>> Thank you, Hannah Rose. Uh, Lawrence,
you your microphone is enabled. You may
speak whenever, sir. Thank you.
>> Yeah, thanks. This is Larry Leman. Um,
I'm a physician, also a member of the
advisory board. Um, a couple of thoughts
here. I would agree with the person who
mentioned being very careful about
requiring a psychiatrist for conditions
if we don't have to because access to
psychiatric care in much of the state is
essentially nil and so it's really hard
to do that for instance on personality
disorders I would be much more specific
about different different ones and some
of them probably should just be
exclusions you know um exclusions but
but other ones I don't think should need
to see a psychiatrist
on the cardiovascular
I'm concerned that actually many of the
conditions that say see a cardiologist
should just be a contraindication.
Severe uncontrolled hypertension to my
knowledge is universally viewed as a a
contraindication. And so that that one
there moderate to severe congestive
heart failure. You many of those
conditions don't seem like they should
go to a cardio. They should just be in
the contra indications category. I've
not seen any guidelines um either for
clinical trials or practice that
wouldn't do that. So I would um
encourage that we consider moving some
of those into contraindications.
>> Yeah. Um I we will actually have a much
longer conversation as soon as we get
these tiers through about um exclusion
criteria. Again, the document that was
provided was more so just trying to show
a visual of what the the words on the
page can look like. Um, but I really do
appreciate the comment.
>> Thanks, Ian, and thanks for the
clarification.
>> Uh, before we get back to uh the
speaker, I just want to get up to par on
the chat. Dr. Lida commented, "I think
it would be important to have a list of
specialists who are approved to be in
this role and it's important to have the
medical specialists to be certified in
psilocybin." Matthew uh commented,
"Hello, my name is Matthew and I'm not
sure if any everyone had to introduce
themselves earlier in the call. A I'm an
oje I hope I said that correctly. I
apologize if I didn't." Descendant and
psilocybin advocate just here to serve
on the subcommittee and serve. Thank
you. Uh Dominic did reply to Dr. Laida
because clinicians and practitioners
would need to be certified through the
program there would be lists of those
who are certified made available and Dr.
Lida confir uh concurs with uh Larry and
include all cardiac conditions is uh
eskeemic cardio cardiammyopathy coronary
artery disease etc. And at menz just
commented dementia also seems like an
issue for informed consent. Thank you
guys for putting my caffeine to work.
And I've enabled your uh microphone
credentials. Lisa, whenever you're
ready, go ahead and unmute yourself.
>> Um hi. So last comment I had also to add
active history of conditions versus um
just a history of conditions. If someone
have active cardiovascular for example
issue that should be taken differently
versus had a history of it. So I think
uh you should include these clauses as
well active versus history of certain
conditions.
>> Thank you.
>> All righty. Are there any other
comments?
All right. So then from what I've heard
there was some mixed opinions about
whether tier three should be um a
specialist practicing within their scope
of lensure
or if that should be an optional. That
sounded like if my understanding is
wrong, feel free to correct me, but
that's sounded like what the debate was
was whether it should be two pime two
different specialists versus a singular
specialist along with the
primary prescriber.
Um,
I will open discussion on that at this
time.
>> All right. and Mets, I've uh enabled
your microphone credentials. You may go
ahead and unmute yourself, please.
>> Sure. Um yeah, actually having uh I
didn't get the email this morning with
the um different conditions that fit
into each tier. And so, um, my sort of
earlier point about a tier three person
with a dual license being able to sort
of see someone individually, kind of
given the actual risk that is outlined
in what was sent out this morning, I I
sort of feel like two people would be
good in a situation like that, just
because it does have, you know, risk of
psychosis. Um, you know, I I guess one
consideration I have is that the
conditions that are presently sort of
approved by the state are, you know, at
least considered three of the four are
federally considered serious mental
illness um with pretty significant
potential for uh retraumatization for
suicide at suicide risk. Um, and so I
don't know that I would necessarily say
that anybody who fits criteria under the
four current conditions just gets
standard protocol because I do sort of
feel like there is um, you know, like no
training program that people are going
to have for psilocybin is going to be
adequate I would say to maybe manage the
risk of some of these conditions. And so
I'm wondering um if and then this might
be a conversation that's more about um
where the different conditions fall, but
if there is something where you know
like they have in Colorado um where you
know there are facilitators that treat
people without risk and then there's a
clinical facilitator level where people
have more risks. Um to me that feels
like it is perhaps better for public
safety just to be able to distinguish
between those two.
Yeah, and that's exactly why I made the
clinical support document because
especially with uh mental health
conditions, they are often don't like to
travel alone. So there's often
coorbidities that we have to take into
account. So that's why I said or that's
why I when creating this I said we need
different amounts of clinical support
for different people. Um so I completely
agree with what you just said that you
know sometimes there are you know risk
of psychosis, risk of um seizures, risk
of other um disorders. So to have those
two specialists, especially while we're
in the time where we're still creating
the educational material, yes, some
exist from Oregon and Colorado, but in
terms of like a truly fleshed out
medical sense, um that doesn't truly
exist to the fullest extent that it
could. So I just want to add another
opinion because two minds often don't
think alike. um and it can give us
insight to some things that we had never
considered. Um but thank you so much.
>> All right. And then just to catch up in
the chat, Dr. Lida commented, "Early
dementia where patients are still
consentable should be fine and in fact
might benefit them greatly." And Hannah
Rose commented, "Yes, two people could
meet needs for support yet that makes it
harder to meet needs of diversity,
equity, and inclusion." And Lisa, I've
went ahead and enabled your microphone
credentials. So, whenever you're ready,
you may unmute yourself, please.
>> Thank you. Just to build on on the
previous comment um in requirements for
this second
practitioner or I would say co-f
facilitator. Again, if that specialist
is not properly trained, I think it's
important to include the clause in this
document on
on what can that second non-licensed
practitioner can do and provide during
the Sabbin session because we also want
to avoid a situation when a second
non-licensed incident facilitation
practice practitioner would intervene in
the session for no reason. So they have
to have very limited
ability to act only if person have
adverse reaction and they can only
assist with specific administration of
medication or discolation of condition
specific uh actions.
>> Thank you.
Next up is
I'm so sorry. Next up is Ellen. Go ahead
and uh unmute yourself whenever you're
ready.
>> Hi, thank you. Um and Ian, thank you. I
really appreciate your openness and
openness to our Discord and um providing
us a safe place to talk about this. One
thing I did want to see if we could get
some clarification on as a team is the
the word psychosis. it's kind of thrown
all over this document and I just have a
little concerns because it's in tier 2,
tier three and tier four and I think we
should really just consider defining
that and being a little more thoughtful
about what exactly we're saying um a lot
of times that that word as a as a if
we're talking about specific symptoms um
because even when we look at tier three
with the delusional disorders that
technically is a psych you know in the
psychotic spectrum. So, I just want to
be as clear as possible with um that
verbiage. Thanks.
>> Yeah, in my mind, the difference between
what is listed in tier three and what is
listed in tier 4 is how active it is.
So, um you could have a history of a
diagnosed delusional disorder without
having active psychosis. And that was
really the only differentiation on why
they're in two different bubbles is um
if they're actively having a psychotic
episode, then they should probably be
excluded. If they had a history, maybe
they've been stable for a long time, but
they do suffer from, you know, treatment
or resistant depression can come with
psychosis. Um PTSD can occasionally come
with psychosis, very less com a little
less common. Um, but in those regards,
that was that was the difference on why
they're included in two spaces. But I do
appreciate the input.
>> Thank you. Next up, we have is James
Brown. James, I've enabled your
microphone. You may begin whenever
you're ready.
>> Morning everyone and thank you Ian for
chairing this again. Um, great start.
Um, one of my only comments really is
timeline. When I look at this document
and I review this and I look at
practicality and application, I say, um,
what's the timeline sometimes, Ian,
behind this stuff? We don't really
doesn't really say specifically, does
this have to be within a week, a day?
Does there need to be a timeline in
this, you know, for these reassessments
or these signoffs? Because some of this
can happen, like you said, within an
acute
uh versus latent type of issue. And and
then if if there is, you know, again,
there's nothing that says again in here
about when that has to occur or is there
a time within it having to occur. That
that was all I had. Thank you. Thank
you. So I personally did not include a
time limit on these things. What I did
was say that if they had a history of
psychosis, they often um they would need
a specialist review. they would have to
get someone with um lensure relevant to
psychiatry in order to sign off and say
this person is stable enough to go
through it. I'm not going to pretend
like I am um a PhD and have all of the
psychology info. I really don't. But I
do know that um
the lensure in order to become a
psychiatrist, a psychiatric nurse
practitioner um a licensed clinical
counselor does give them a lot of
information and insight that I um may go
through but haven't at up till this
point. So that's why I had personally
deferred. But if you think that we need
to um
write those out, that could be something
we discuss um when we actually go uh
discuss the different conditions and
which ones we're putting in, you know,
which tiers.
But thank you.
>> Thank you. And then uh just to catch up
in the chat, Hannah Rose commented,
"Yes, the word psychosis is not a
traumainformed word from a social work
perspective." And Allan commented,
"History of psychosis includes
delusional disorder." And as of right
now, Ian, since no one has their hand
up, I pass it back to you.
>> Perfect. So in terms of just the not the
diagnosis that are in the chart but just
the overline
um
structure of the clinical support
framework.
Are there any other additional comments
before we take a vote?
>> Uh Dr.
>> Dr. Alita, I've enabled your microphone.
You may unmute yourself whenever you're
ready.
>> Thank you so much and thank you for for
this uh discussion and how you've
created the tears and I think it's
great. Um the one of the uh thoughts
that I have is to have um you know
licensed practitioners like you know to
have a almost like a you know in
medicine we have for oncology we have
what we call tumor boards which is where
a group of specialists physicians get
together and they review difficult cases
and you know This makes me think of
psychedelic boards review with having
two or three expert physicians who from
maybe different disciplines including
psychiatry incl you know in the state of
New Mexico were so underserved from a
medical perspective. I mean 300
physicians left in in a year um because
of malpractice laws that we're hopefully
changing in this session. But because of
that um we are so underresourced
um that as Larry was mentioning I
wouldn't just go by psychiatry because
we just don't have that many um but if
we have a you know let's say a
psilocybin
boards you know for for those two or
three physicians who meet up maybe twice
a month to review the tough cases the
complex cases is um and they can advise
the community members on how to proceed
and maybe further testing is necessary.
Maybe we need to look at a scores. Maybe
we we got to you know administer
personality uh tests and different
different tools um for the patient to
really assess them further. Um, and I
think that would be really informative
and
really important safeguard for the more
complex cases and and maybe many of them
would be, you know, hey, we see this and
they don't meet criteria for this
treatment at this time. Um, just a
thought.
Thank you.
>> I appreciate your input. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Dr. Lita. And and uh just to
catch up with the chat, uh Alan
commented, "It seems like it would be
impractical impractical to have such a
board of all physicians." Uh Deborah
commented, "H99 for MedMal was passed."
Shane McDaniel commented, "The
malpractice bill passed House and Senate
just needs governor to sign from what I
understand." And an commented, "Sounds
like an excellent idea to have a board,
particularly if this consult would not
cost more for the patient." And uh
whenever you are ready Dr. Lee
>> um Mrs. Larry um the um one one concern
about the structure here it looks to me
and maybe I'm reading this wrong that if
you had like PTSD and you don't have
another diagnosis that you're you know
implied that you don't need any other
support. But I I'd like to be really
careful with that because like PTSD um
includes complex PTSD that that really
needs to have someone involved. I mean
I've seen just in our research work, you
know, people come out with um come out
having a lot of trouble with their
trauma there. So I think there needs to
be even as we look at the the diagnosis
kind of look at them you know look at
the substance use disorder look at the
PTSD and look at which of those need
additional help even though they don't
have another diagnosis.
>> Okay. Thank you for that
>> and in the chat uh AB commented such a
great point Dr. Leman, high risk of
retraumatization, relapse, etc. And
Hannah Rose commented, "Consider social
workers as trauma informed specialists."
Back to you, Ian. So,
one, the reason why I I hadn't included
um those disorders specifically is
because those patients are who the
program is entirely made for at this
point. Um so I hadn't intentionally
spelled out that you know they may need
to be extra precautious but I have um at
least in my work in the dosage committee
worked on you know providing
subperceptual doses to PTSD patients for
the fact that it allows us to you know
test the waters a little bit. We can
prevent that retraumatization. We can
prevent greater um distress on the
patients by providing them a lower dose.
So, I'm not saying that we shouldn't
take extra care with patients with PTSD
or SUD, but we should, in my opinion,
that's about leaving it up to the
patient cuz that's who the program was
made for. But I would be fully open to
disagreement on that point. Um, I will
turn it over to the next speaker.
>> Thank you, Ian.
So, uh, Court, your microphone
credentials have been enabled. Whenever
you're ready, please unmute yourself.
>> Uh, good morning and thank you, uh,
Court Wing from the Psychedelics and
Pain Association. Since you brought up
subperceptual doses, I'm noticing in the
four qualifying conditions, PTSD,
substance use disorders, end of life,
and treatment resistant depression, all
four are birectional with chronic pain.
Chronic pain often is something that can
be dosed at subperceptual doses daily if
not weekly. Is it going to be necessary
to have uh accompanying practitioners if
they're taking
um these medications for say cluster
headache which usually is on a pulse
regimen of one to two grams not at the
same level that we would see say a 25
milligram of a synthetic psilocybin
being applied. Is there any way to
create exemptions for people that are
essentially taking what's colloally
referred to as a micro dose or a mini
dose?
At this time, there is not a there's not
room in the current law for us to weaken
the restrictions on that. The law
requires that we give each patient a
preparation admin administration and
integration session. Meaning that it
would be very difficult to provide a uh
a maintenance dose if you will of
psilocybin for those type of um
conditions.
Once we have the program launched and we
can um you know have some ground to
stand on with
the legislature and say look how this
has worked out. we haven't had any real
problems. Um, and we can see that
patients could be benefiting from this
once, you know, the evidence is more
concrete in support of that. Um, then we
would be able to
go in with a much stronger argument than
if we try to allow it right out the gate
when they specifically told us we need
those three sessions.
>> Okay. All right. Thank you.
Thank you, Court.
Before I proceed uh to unmute the next
participant, I just want to apply uh
excuse me, catch up to the chat. Hannah
Rose commented, "Yes, patient
self-determination is the first step in
effective social work practice, which
applies to client choice of treatment."
And Eileen Brewer just commented, "I'm
so sorry I missed the beginning of the
meeting, but does this document create a
world where other conditions will be
difficult to add later? There's going to
be a lot of work in adding conditions at
any rate since the bill says other
conditions approved by the department
and other work groups have already begun
discussing what to add.
Alan, your microphone has been enabled.
Whenever you're ready, go ahead and
proceed.
>> Thanks again. One other thing um that
occurred to me is maybe it would help
the group if we defined when we talk
about the standard support that we also
are defining kind of what the what our
checklist or what our medical kind of
clearance is or what our clearance kind
of in general is. Maybe having an
understanding of what that, you know,
having that full-sight history of a
cardiovascular history and that kind of
information would maybe help kind of
know what we're being what we're asking
even from the start. So that would maybe
help understand what would fall between
the different tiers if that makes sense.
>> Yeah. Thank you.
>> Thank you, James. your microphone has
been enabled. Whenever you're ready, go
ahead and unmute yourself.
>> Ian and everyone, um, you know, my
thought on the language around, you
know, and I know Ian, you sent that
document out, um, but in category 4, you
know, just my really thought around that
is the language around re-referral. You
know, it shouldn't really be a hard
stop. Yes, they don't need psilocybin at
this time, but these people sometimes
are at the end of the line, we would
call it, right? They've failed therapy.
They failed western medicine. Maybe
they've even failed, you know,
alternative medicine, and maybe they
failed other plant-based medicines. And
so, the wording and what we need to wrap
our minds around with the with category
4 is yes, it's a hard stop right now. Um
maybe maybe down the line they qualify
or maybe they don't. But also maybe they
just need different services, right? But
I just want to be really, you know,
really, you know, thoughtful about those
people because in Oregon when we see
that, it's it's one of those things
where we don't want them to think that
this is the end. Does that make sense?
We don't want them to think that, oh, I
I came to psychedelics thinking that I'm
going to get help and then they just
tell me no. Right? And and we don't want
them to walk away thinking that, right?
And so I just want everybody to think
around that and you know what what what
can we do to mitigate or offer them you
know to help them get back in the
pathway of other services and then you
know and then and then be reevaluated
later you know maybe has to say you know
for re-evaluation there it's a hard stop
but definitely there still should be
re-evaluated
or something that's all thank you
Yeah, thank you. Um, so currently there
is not a re-evaluation mechanism. It
there is a specification that placement
in tier 4 does not constitute a
permanent exclusion and may be
reconsidered if clinical circumstance
changes. Um, as you know in Oregon, one
of the big exclusions is lithium in the
past 30 days. Well, if they stop taking
it and hopefully are stabilized with
something else, um, then they would be
eligible as soon as that wash out period
ended. It was never supposed to be this.
You're kicked out and you're kicked out
forever. That's why I've kind of
reserved very active states. So, active
suicidal homicidal ideation, active
psychosis um for those because give us
some time to re-evaluate, let a
specialist check in and then we can we
can work on that. Um but it was never
supposed to be a just hard stop.
Thank you.
Thank you, Ian. Uh before we proceed to
unmute the next participant, I'm just
going to catch up in the chat. Uh, so
Michelle commented, "Tier 2 and three
patients should require more
preparation, two to three preparation
sessions instead of one for tier one,
and more follow-up, two to four sessions
than tier one or one to two." Hannah
Rose commented, "Yes, distribution of
services is another area of social work
specialization."
Uh, Caya McKenzie commented, "I have a
concern about a limited number of
gatekeepers who would enable access to
this medicine. As a naturopathic doctor
for 25 plus years, using homeopathy and
botanical medicines in all forms is
still met with tremendous resistance and
skepticism. Take up by those able to
approve access has the potential to dog
down utilization as they bring
themselves up to speed on research
supporting psilocybin medicine.
Conversely, will those eligible as
gatekeepers be able to keep up with
screening those interested and who could
benefit from medical psilocybin, or will
their practices become revolving doors
of folks seeking approval for care? And
Katherine's retort to Michelle was, "In
my opinion, there should always be at
least three prep sessions, never just
one." Dr. Laida, thank you for allowing
me to catch up in the chat. Your
microphone has been enabled. Whenever
you're ready, go ahead and unmute
yourself.
>> Thank you so much. Um, I'm going to, um,
I love that discussion that James
brought up and Ian, thank you for your
clarification around it as well. One
point that James brought up that I love
is being able to offer other services to
individuals who may not meet these
particular criteria. Um, for example,
those with schizophrenia, we know that,
you know, look up Dr. Chris Palmer from
um, Harvard. He is you utilizing
ketogenic diet for his schizophrenic
patients who are the worst of the worst
in the world that he sees at Harvard and
50% of them who are able to in adhere to
that particular um nutritional intake
they have gotten better without
hallucinations without auditory you know
visual hallucinations. So, it's very
powerful to be able to help our
population not just with psychedelics,
but maybe open the doors for people who
are seeking this medicine for their just
living well, right? They everybody wants
to have a high quality of life, do the
things they want to be able to do. And
it may not be psychedelics. This may be
a gate for us to bring in people to
connect them with amazing resources that
we have in our community without
psychedelics as well. Um so I really
like that um James brought that up.
Thank you.
>> Thank you Dr. Lida. Shane, your
microphone has been enabled. Whenever
you're ready, go ahead and unmute
yourself. Thank you.
>> Can you hear me?
Yes sir.
>> Okay. Um this may not be a issue but um
would it ever be the case where a
patient
does not provide truthful
information
um that they have one of these
conditions that would um negate them
being considered for the treatment. And
so like somebody that that does have
psych uh you know uh uh psychotic
episodes or uh heart conditions or any
of that stuff but doesn't
um communicate that and then they get
the treatment
anyways.
And then what if that if that would be
the case what would be the liability of
the provider
if that makes sense.
So assessment is usually done by some
form of medical provider whether it be a
nurse, a doctor, uh you know whoever is
actually going to be prescribing the
medication. Um and in that vein the
doctor is not responsible for
a patient lying to them. They are
supposed to assess and
that is a really big part. However,
with psychiatric conditions, there's
often a lot more subjective data than
objective data and sometimes that can be
distorted. So, I do recognize that that
is an issue. However,
I don't believe that that would cause
liability onto a doctor.
I am not a liability professional. This
is not legal advice.
Um, but I do believe that it would defer
off of the doctor, especially if they're
lying about a history that they were
aware of.
Thank you, Ian. I'm just going to catch
up in the chat. Uh Eileen had responded
to Katherine. I think it would depend on
the patient. That's a lot of added
expense, too. And Katherine's retort
was, "I disagree. Cultivating a
relationship with the client is
important, and proper prep is a high
indicator to successful outcomes, just
like integration prep is so critical."
And Hannah Rose commented, "This is
where a psychosocial assessment comes
in." again another special
specialization of social workers
and no one has their hand up at this
time Ian. So back to you.
Alrighty. So
I still haven't
heard too much
disagreement with the actual four tiers.
Not saying the conditions on the tiers,
but of the actual four tiers that we
currently have, a standard support, an
enhanced clinical support, a um
specialist supported care, and not
appropriate for participation at this
time.
Um
can we go ahead and have a vote? Uh
Jorge, can you pull up the hand
instructions?
Perfect. Um, I did see Larry's hand just
come up, so I will go ahead and let him
speak before we move on.
>> Yeah. Thank Thank you, Ian. I I just
like to say what I said before a little
bit, but maybe more specifically that
there's somewhere in it should indicate
that simply being in tier one does not
mean you don't need more support because
there clearly are situations where you
do, you know, uncontrolled fentanyl use
or substance use disorders, complex
PTSD, and and I I just think some
clarification whether it's an asterct or
somewhere in the writing to indicate
that that many people will need some
extra support without while still being
in that uh uh category one.
>> So would um keeping the language the
same it would say proceed with standard
protocol patients may
request
additional
clinical support
>> well and you know and I and I don't mean
to talk against patient autonomy but
some of it is more than that. I mean, if
somebody is like using actively using
fentanyl four times a day and they say I
don't need any more support, I think
that we for their safety do need to have
a boundary put in there. My suggestion
would be that there's and I'm not sure
which committee should do that should
look at people in the in the in the
category. In other words, substance use
disorder, you know, uncontrolled ongoing
fentanyl use, um, uh, you know, complex
PTSD and and kind of drill down a little
bit to which of the core categories, you
know, may need more support. And I don't
think that needs to happen now, but I I
just want to advocate for that happening
for for providing the best care to
people. I think people with complex PTSD
can be excellent candidates for
psilocybin care, but they need a
different container than somebody with a
single episode of PTSD from, you know,
from violence or such. I just want to
make sure we don't establish a structure
that doesn't have specific um uh
guidelines within each condition.
>> So, would you be okay with saying
patients or the provider may request
additional clinical support at the time
of assessment?
Yeah, I I would I guess I'm suggesting
that that as we go through with the
program that we try to drill down a
little bit on each of the conditions to
give some um advice to the um uh to the
providers.
>> Perfect. Well, I will go ahead and add
that amendment. The clinical support
support framework has just been posted
in the chat as amended.
All right. So, what we're going to go
ahead and do is if you are in support of
the clinical support framework as
amended, please raise your hand at this
time.
And it looks like there are 10 hands
raised.
>> Perfect. 10 in affirmation. Please put
your hands down.
Perfect. And then if you are in um
opposition of the clinical support
framework, please raise your hand at
this time.
With
zero in opposition, the clinical support
framework as amended has been adopted by
the committee. We can now go ahead
and move on to
Would
you guys rather do the
um exclusion criteria or would you
rather look over psychiatric and
neurological conditions in terms of the
next step? I don't think we're going to
have time to do both.
Katherine has her hand up. Catherine,
your microphone is enabled. Whenever
you're ready, go ahead.
>> Sorry about that. That was actually an
accident. Um, but I would like to talk
about the um exclusions if possible.
>> Okay. Yeah. Then let's go ahead and move
over to the exclusion criteria. It looks
like there's a couple comments saying
that as well.
Katherine, your microphone has been
enabled. Go ahead.
>> I think the first thing that I noticed
that was kind of missing from the list
is age restrictions. Is that something
we're going to examine? Are we going to
allow, you know, any age? Are we going
to stick to adults? Um, I just noticed
that I know you said Ian that it was
just a rough draft, but I just noticed
that wasn't listed and I wanted to
mention that. Um, I also have a couple
of other conditions I want to discuss. I
don't know if we're ready to do that
now. I can hold off if not.
>> Yeah, no worries. So, what we're going
to be doing right now is looking at the
um disqualifying conditions and
disqualifying medications. Um, so if
they fall into either of those, then we
would be happy to discuss them.
>> Okay. Um, I' I'd noticed that unmanaged
diabetes was not listed. Um, I think
that's something we definitely need to
examine. I think if um, diabetes is
managed and maybe a doctor's um, report
associated with that, then I say we we
can give a green light. But if not, I
think that's something that needs to be
added. Um, I also think we should be
looking at seizure uh seizure history um
certain conditions. I know that that was
something that um was discussed in my
training.
So, yeah, that would be it. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Katherine. I'm just going to
catch up with the chat here before we
proceed to unmute the next participant.
Michelle commented, "Technically, there
are three interactions. Initial inquiry,
medical and psychiatric screening,
preparation sessions, and then actual
dosing sessions. With higher risk tier 2
to three, the practitioner makes a
determination on additional prep
sessions." Deborah commented, "Part of
complete medical screening, a prescriber
should acquire previous medical
records." And commented, "Yes, people
will need safety plans with all of these
conditions." and Katherine commented
that the provider should decide if they
need more support for tier one. Uh Ian
posted the clarification for the uh
language on there and Hannah Rose
commented agreed making tiers for
assessment is essential. Uh James Brown
commented exclusion criteria and Alan
commented is there a standard set for
assessment and ability to provide
informed consent? And finally with an
agree with what Katherine said about
seizure disorders.
No one has their hand up at this as of
this time, Ian. So, it's back to you.
>> All right. So the original ones that I
had um considered use of lithium in the
past 30 days um active psychosis, acute
intoxication,
history of hallucinogen induced
psychosis, uncontrolled seizures,
uncontrolled diabetes malitis, current
suicidal or homicidal ideiation with
intent plan or inability to maintain
safety. Um,
the first question I guess I'll ask is,
does anyone think any of those
conditions need to be stricken, stried,
one of those? Um, from the current list.
All right,
I see no hands up. So, does anyone have
any additional um conditions that we
still need to add?
Right.
All right. So, first up is Alan. Alan,
I've enabled your microphone. You may
unmute yourself whenever you're ready.
>> Thanks. I know this document keeps
moving around, but um I just was wanting
to add what I put in the chat, which is
inability to provide informed consent.
Thanks.
>> Thank you, Alan.
Dr. Leman.
>> Yeah, I'd again like to advocate I think
both myself and Dr. Ida felt like all of
the cardiovascular criterias don't need
to see a cardiologist. They just should
be contraindications. Uncontrolled
hypertension, moderate to severe
congestive heart failure. Um I I don't
think any of those are appropriate for
for psilocybin. So I would move those
into exclusions.
>> Thank you, Dr. Leman.
All right. And Hannah Rose, whenever
you're ready, your microphone has been
enabled. go ahead and unmute yourself,
please.
>> Thank you. I just want to advocate for
um some different languaging around
psychosis um because of how it is not
traumainformed in our practice um
perspective as social workers. Um so,
um let's see here.
Could there be
what other words could we use? You know,
I guess that's what I'm I'm curious
about.
>> I personally don't know what word other
than psychosis. I personally also am not
the biggest fan of it. I just couldn't
find something that
met the criteria of that word. Um,
>> I have a an idea. Um, okay. I'm just
kind of throwing an idea out here. Um,
could we make a little amendment? Um,
and I could do some research with my
social work professors and mentors in
the program and then just come back with
you and see what they say.
>> Okay. Yeah. Um,
so
I will pull active psychosis to be on
its own
thing. If we really want to worry about
the the word part of it. I'm going to
wait a little bit to see if we um if
anyone else here has a better idea than
I do. Um, and then failing that, then we
can push it off.
Thank you. Uh in the chat just to catch
up uh court had commented multiple case
reports in a recent trial show lowd dose
psilocybin is effective in reversing the
symptom profile of type 2 diabetes.
Deborah commented uncontrolled
hypertension and thank you Jorge for uh
putting the copy of the placement of
proposed exclusion criteria. Shane
McDaniel commented regarding diabetes
are we talking about type one or type
two or both? Alan said thank you Dr.
Leman and I think we should use what we
call it from a diagnostic perspective uh
than proposing psychotic spectrum.
Katherine proposed active psychotic
episodes and Eileen commented does a
history of hallucination include include
induced psychosis, excuse me, indicate
that it will be a probability in the
future. Is there research to support
that? I don't think it should be an
exclusion criteria.
James, thank you for being patient with
me while I caught up with the chat. Your
microphone has been enabled. You may
unmute yourself whenever you're ready,
sir.
>> Thank you, sir. Um, one comment on this
Ian in group um was poly substance. I
don't see anything that includes the
words um with like cocaine or anything
that would be inetamine based. Um that
is in the literature some about poly
substance being excluded. Um just those
two uh just those two substances um
would be opinion of of what I'm thinking
on uh because they can control your
blood pressure and some other things can
happen with cardiac as well uh those
interactions
um
and as well as the other thing I think
with with these are considered to me
kind of like hard stops
um you know in the medical world these
definitely need to be looked at and
addressed again. And again, we need a
pathway um for
uh these people to make sure that they
um that we use the right wording that we
use the right um things here with these
people cuz if we hard stop somebody that
is psychologically going to affect them
as well. And so just just to throw that
out there again about that concern about
what are we doing with these people if
we say hard stop um and the addition of
again those poly substances need to be
in there um because that is occurring
with most people still. Um thank you so
much.
>> Thank you. Um I guess as a followup,
do you think we need to specify within
like acute intoxication a specific
exclusion for um like stimulant use or
just DC all poly substance?
>> No, I think you need to be specific on
which ones. Um like you were saying uh
maybe to me it's cocaine, it's an high
use and
um people are going to be on opioids for
pain. and they're going to be on other
poly medications or other poly naturals
um or other poly plant-based medicines.
Um I think that's okay. Um I just think
that there should just be a few of those
that I said um exclusion there
specifically.
>> Cool. Thank you.
>> Thank you. uh to catch up here on the
chat since no one has their hand uh
raises this time is uh Hannah Rose
commented, "I'd like psychotic spectrum
languaging." Uh Dr. Leeman commented,
"Agree. Active stimulant use as
contraindication."
Hannah Rose commented, "When there is a
hard stop, this is where a social worker
can be referred to the client for
supportive services." And Michelle
commented, "No hard stops. There needs
to be hope for these people, not now."
and mens commented was or asked wasn't
stimulant use disorder one of the
diagnosises included acute intoxication
makes sense though
back to you Ian
yeah um so in kind of agreement with the
comments so stimulant use disorder
wasn't specifically mentioned it was
under the umbrella of substance use
disorder um but yeah there is a very
real possibility that someone might have
might qualify for this program. So I do
also concur with Larry that um and James
that if especially because psilocybin
has such an dramatic impact on the
cardiovascular system that we take
special care to you know exclude um
those
okay
all right does anyone else see anything
that they feel is missing from this
list.
And looks like Katherine Waro's hand is
up. Katherine, your microphone is
enabled. Go ahead and uh unmute
yourself.
>> I This may sound ignorant, but is age a
condition? Do we want to include age or
not?
>> Personally, I have not seen enough
studies on the efficacy in children. If
someone has alternative information,
please let me know.
>> Dr. Leman, go ahead.
>> Um, I would say we don't have to have an
upper age limit in our one of our
studies of psilocybin. Um, we do a 94
year old. So, I I do not think there
should be an upper age limit. You know,
a lot of people will have
contraindications, but I think upper age
should not be a should not be a
contraindication.
Thank you Dr. Leman and also he had
placed in the chat could say active
stimulant use within last 5 days and
Deborah just commented 18 plus best at
this time as per studies. Hannah Rose
your microphone credentials are enabled.
Go ahead and unmute yourself whenever
you're ready.
>> Thank you. I agree with um the doctor
that just spoke and um yeah so no um I
don't think there should be age limit on
this. Um my teacher in psychedelic
application works with children um micro
doing and she does end of care um end of
life care work with whole families and
so the whole family all age r ages will
micro dose while the client is going
through that process and so yeah I just
want to agree um no age limits and then
um I'd also just like to speak to the
kind of this hard stop thing so it's
like there's going to hard stops here
most likely, right? We already have
disqualifying conditions and for the
concern of what happens to those people.
Well, this is where um the profession of
social work is so beautiful. Then we get
to work with these people and get them
so they can qualify. And that's the type
of social worker I want to be in this
program.
>> Thank you, Hannah. Uh in the chat, uh
Katherine commented, "Agree with Larry
about no upper age limits." Craig asked,
"Has HPPPD in extreme cases ever been
considered as an exclusion in other
state programs?" And an commented,
"HPPPD isn't an exclusion criteria in
Colorado or Oregon." Meredith, I
appreciate your patience while I caught
up with the chat. Your microphone has
been enabled. You may unmute yourself
whenever you're ready.
>> Um thank you. I was just curious about
like concurrent
uh use with other psychedelics or
hallucinogenics and I'm not sure what it
says in the literature or if like there
needs to be scape guards in time limits
um if people are using like MDMA or LSD
or something else.
>> Thank you.
With regard to that aspect, I think I
would put that under a um
under a clinical warning of serotonin
syndrome or potentially a um specialist
review. I don't know that I would full
on exclude it, especially given that
like LSD is um you build a cross
tolerance to psilocybin. So that
shouldn't really cause too many issues.
I'm not well enough educated on MDMA to
say that. But um yeah, anyway, next is
an
you are correct and your microphone
credentials have been enabled. you may
unmute yourself whenever you're ready.
>> Um, yeah, I think I have two thoughts. I
mean, you know, I tend to be I think a
little bit risk averse as a clinician.
Um, and I think for right now, I think
keeping it to adults, um, 18 and over
makes sense, at least until there's more
of a research base to support the use of
children and adolescence.
Um, I guess from a practical standpoint,
um, for Department of Health, what do we
need, you know, how how how
adaptable is this document going
forward? If we were to sort of say 18
and over, is that written in stone?
Um, even if we said 18 or over, it
wouldn't be written in stone. The board
and even this committee could revise the
recommendation. Um so it wouldn't
necessarily lock it in. Generally before
we the board finally signs off on things
we will um verify that it is all good
cuz once we let it out to the department
that's when it becomes a lot harder to
reverse. But um if new data comes out
and we need to adjust something like
let's say we said no minors then um
we could adjust that going forward as
soon as there was um new evidence to
support it.
Then I I would be in agreement with
Katherine that that 18 and um sort of
under the age of 18 would be a
disqualifying I I wouldn't say a
condition but circumstance.
Thank you an uh before I unmute the next
participant I'm just going to catch up
with the chat. Alan commented HPPPD more
in LSD not psilocybin. Deborah
commented, "Ketamine can be a great prep
tool for macro dosing of psilocybin."
Kaya was just asking for clarification
of the HPPD acronym, which Alan and
Craig confirmed as hallucinogen
persisting perceptual disorder. Lisa,
again, much obliged for giving me
patience while I caught up with that.
Your microphone has been enabled.
Whenever you're ready, go ahead and
unmute yourself.
Just a friendly reminder, you may unmute
yourself by uh clicking on the
microphone icon
and unfortunately Lisa, we cannot hear
you. Um
>> hello.
>> Most there you are.
>> Oh, thank you. Um so in terms of age um
I would push 21 and older to access. I
think um especially for young adults we
have to be really careful. They brain is
still information until 25 years old and
I see it as a high risk to administer
psilocybin to even 18 years old um
adolescence.
So I think 21 years old would be
appropriate. Uh the second comment I had
is for pregnant women. Are you including
or excluding pregnant women? I see that
as a high risk as well. Um simply
because we have a lot of uh we don't
have enough data for pregnant women and
psychedelic use and the effect on a uh
child. But we do have a lot of studies
on alcohol use for pregnant women and we
see um a lot of adverse reactions. Um so
I would include that as well.
>> Thank you, Lisa.
As of this time, Ian Oh, I stand
corrected. James Brown, your microphone
has been enabled. Whenever you're ready,
sir.
Thank you again. You know, I'm really
torn on this guys because in in the end
here's here's the debate I'm having is
the literature which again there's going
to be limited literature, right? Because
of the patient population.
So the literature right now states most
of the studies are 18 and above. That
makes sense, right? Because of what and
where this drug and you know this sat,
right? Um, if we look at New Mexico
traditionally in cultures
that are outside the normal big city and
we're talking on the reservations here,
they introduce psilocybin and other
psychedelics at a very early age and
they've been doing this for thousands of
years. If you go back to Maria Sabina
and all their culture and what they
provide to us and what they can what we
can learn from them is that this is a
family traditional medicine. And I want
to make sure we remind ourselves of that
in a western medicine model, how can we
traditionally respect and honor some of
their cultural in our cultural beliefs?
And so 18 is is the marker for studies.
Um, but again, this is a thought process
of what we can do and and a lot of these
people are in high school are early and
they're and they're starting at 16 and
they're doing a lot of poly substances
and they're doing a lot of they're
exposed to a lot of things and sometimes
they've had failures to medications by
the time they're at 8 16 even. And so I
just want everybody to make sure they're
thinking with that lens and that thought
process. if you decide on something
that's 18 restricted, 21 restricted,
these are big things and and some of
these people will still need services
and help. And so, you know, 18, if we
start there, you know, with the ability
to go down maybe to 16, you know, as
studies and as research will come out
and show, and again, the traditional
beliefs of New Mexicans and on the
reservations, they do start this very
early.
Thank you.
>> Yeah. And I think the age thing is such
a a
big aspect in how we're conducting this
program because you mentioned the kids
who are who are 16 and had already
failed medication. Um that would have
been me. And so I do think it is very
important that we allow access to these
medications and to services because
again if you have treatment resistant
depression it can feel like there is no
option for you. So, in order to address
this very um
controversial topic, since we've heard a
lot from both sides, we're why don't we
have a vote on whether or not there
should be a lower age limit? Um, so
Jorge, can you bring up the hand slide
again?
And this is not in relation to anything
else in that exclusion criteria. This is
just the most controversial part is
going to be age. So, um I want to get it
out of the way. So, once that is brought
up, I will take a quick vote on what we
are going to do for the H.
Perfect. So, if you are in support of
having the medical psilocybin program
accept patients
only 18 years or older, raise your hand.
And I currently see seven. Oh, going up.
Uh, seven hands raised. Eight. Nine.
10. 10 hands raised.
>> All right. Right. So, I have 10 votes in
affirmation. Can I get everyone to put
your hands down?
Anyone who thinks that
there should be no lower age limit,
please raise your hand.
early three hand four hands Ian.
>> So we have four against 10 in favor.
That means overwhelmingly we do want a
um age limit. So
we will go ahead and put all
participants in the medical psilocybin
program should be 18 years of age or
older.
All right.
Um, everyone can put their hands down
and then if you would like to speak, you
may keep your hands up. And we are still
working on these um disqualifying
conditions and disqualifying
medications. So, if you have any
comments or things you would like to
add, um, we will go forward with that.
>> Thank you, Ian. Before I unmute the next
participant, I'm just going to catch up
with the chat once more. Allan had made
a comment to see the entire section of
the document. It seemed to be cut off on
the end or take out the extra notes from
Oregon. Hannah Rose commented, "High
high risk medically for pregnant women
and children is one perspective. What
about cultural considerations? Where
have cultures been working with
psilocybin among all populations?
Corrections which not where?" Katherine
commented, "I agree that ceremonial
ceremonially psilocybin is administered
as young as 8 years old. This is why I
wanted us to have this discussion. I
believe that psilocybin can help
teenagers but we don't have studies.
Hannah Rose commented then we do need to
do research and get these studies on the
table. Dr. Leman had commented agree
with age 18 until more data. FDA has
stated we'll support such studies on
future. Thank you again for Dominic for
posting how to uh do the instructions
with Microsoft teams. And then Deborah
commented if a minor is treated that
results in a dire consequence. This
presents a huge liability for all
involved. Uh court, since you have your
hand raised, I'm going to go ahead and
enable your microphone and whenever
you're ready, you may unmute yourself.
>> Thank you. I just wanted to highlight um
there are multiple anecdotal reports of
psilocybin being effective as well as uh
early case studies effective for uh
reducing um both insulin resistance as
well as blood sugar levels. And now we
have a new study showing that it's
effective for um reducing a highfat um
type 2 diabetes um both in terms of
obesity
uh liver toxicity uh decreasing uh
triglyceride levels as well as blood
glucose. So uh I understand there may be
concern about the uh cardio impacts of
uh uncontrolled diabetes but at the same
time I would like to encourage people to
look at the research showing that
psilocybin may be actually one of the
more effective things for uh reducing it
even in people that are taking med
medicine to reduce their A1C numbers and
the like. Thanks.
>> Thank you Court. Next up is Shane.
Shane, your microphone has been enabled.
Whenever you're ready, go ahead and
unmute yourself, please.
>> Yeah. I um kind of want to get into this
diabetes talk a little bit more. Is
these are these results you're seeing um
direct results of the medicine or are
they indirect in that somebody is now
able to be more in control of their
life, in control of their diet, in
control of their um
um
um their their ability to
think properly rather than just being in
a complete state of confusion and
complete state of depression or anxiety
and therefore their diet is terrible. Um
I just want to know if it's if if it's
more directly
um a result or more like I say an
indirect result um that more aligned
with other healings that took place that
you know I think I've said enough there.
Hopefully that made sense.
Thank you, Shane. And in the chat, Dr.
Leman just commented, "Please share
reference on psilocybin and diabetes."
As of this time, Ian, no one has their
hand raised up, so it's back to you.
All righty.
Um so for our um document going to go
ahead and once again
post it in the chat just so that
everyone is able to review and see
everything um even when we're scrolling.
So is there anything else we feel is
missing at this time?
Right. I see no hands. So, we will go
ahead and go for a vote. All righty.
Jorge, I know I make you switch screens
all the time, but will you please pull
up the hands?
Oh, we did not discuss pregnancy. He is
she is so right. Um,
>> Ian Ian, we had several people wanting
to move the cardiovascular into
exclusions and myself and Dr. Fatimi.
So, we may need some more discussion on
that unless you've moved them already.
>> Yeah, I had put uncontrolled
hypertension and congestive heart
failure. Were there others that you
wanted to put in there?
See
in the chat. Alan asked, "Is semic heart
disease valvular disease?"
And uh and put pregnancy and I uh Alan,
I thought pregnancy was on there.
Alan just comment uh excuse me Eileen
just commented I think it might be
useful to have time to review literature
before voting on this and court has
posted a PubMed uh hyperlink.
Kiana just commented. Larry, was it you
who suggested specifically moderate or
severe CHF rather than just CHF
and Hannah Rose uh just yes, let's
review literature before voting.
>> Okay, that sounds great. Um,
so if you guys would like to review um,
literature, I say we can have this sent
out potentially. Um,
we can have this sent out. Everyone can
get a chance to review it. See if um,
they have any additional can these that
was the wrong document.
Um, that was all of the different ones
we were going to consider today for
psychiatry, but we did not have time.
Here's the actual one of the exclusion
criteria that we were talking about
today. Um, please review it. Look for
any data um or review your sources. Make
sure that we're not being overly strict
or overly lenient. And um I think we can
adjourn for today. Does that sound good?
I have added pregnancy. I just it's not
in that copied one.
Pregnancy/ breastfeeding.
>> Cool.
>> Lisa,
>> microphone has been Oh, I'm so sorry.
Your microphone now has been enabled.
you may go ahead and unmute yourself
whenever you're ready.
>> Um, in terms of the breastfeeding, I
don't think breastfeeding should be uh
exclusion. I do believe pregnancy should
be definitely exclusion. However,
breastfeeding
um there's a lot of evidence and status
already shown that you can do pump and
dump and you'll be uh safe to um to
breastfeed after that. So, that should
not be an exclusion.
>> Okay.
Thank you, Lisa. James, your microphone
has been enabled. Whenever you're ready,
go ahead, sir.
>> Thank you, sir. Again, I just wanted to
echo that same uh comment. Pregnancy,
yes, breastfeeding uh pump and dump
method until until it washes out, which
is not very long, couple days.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you, James. Dr. Leman, go ahead.
I'm agreeing. There actually is some
data now on a drug that's being studied
that breaks into psilocin in the
bloodstream and it does seem to be gone
within like 24 hours. So I think 48
hours of pump and discard is is very
reasonable.
>> All righty.
Okay. So, I've posted the new proposed
exclusion criteria that we will think
on. Um, so when would you guys like to
have your next meeting?
So, if you guys wanted to meet
relatively quickly after, we could do
next week or we could do the 6th of
March. It would be after the next
medical psilocybin advisory board
meeting. Um, does that sound good? March
6th.
Let's see. As far as there are
um couple other committees that day, so
it would have to be
>> I I'll put that
>> I think the only slot for the sixth that
would be available would be um 3 to 5
p.m.
>> Um would you guys be okay with the 6 at
3:00 to 5:00 p.m.?
We do have one of the training and
education uh one to three.
So uh maybe a little window in between
for folks. As you can see, I put the
training uh all the uh uh committee
meetings in the chat. So there are
actually two.
Sorry. Uh
>> yeah, we can um so we can either do it
on not a Friday. So what about March
4th?
Yep. Yeah, we don't have any any other
committee meetings or anything that I'm
seeing on the calendar for that day. So,
that we should be pretty open uh for the
4th.
>> Okay. March 4th at 10:00 a.m.
>> Thank you, Johnny.
And folks, uh, here I have the slide up,
uh, and I've also put it in the chat,
uh, how to submit public records. Uh, if
you want to submit public comment, uh,
please send it to the medical.silocybin
dooh.nm.gov
uh, email and type the committee in the
subject line. And, uh, don't send an
entire document. you can send a
hyperlink uh and be specific like what
you're referenced to rather than just
sending a whole article without context.
Uh that will help all our chairs uh uh
for that matter uh in in our advisory
board. That eases that some of that
where in the past we've been they've
been sent already thousands of documents
without sometimes without contacts and
it would help them uh rather than we
don't want Ian up all night. He has
other work to do. Um so uh documents
limited to no more than three pages,
letter size and 10.5 font. And please
also include in the document your uh
full legal name and any organizational
affiliations. Please send it by 5:00
p.m. tomorrow.
>> Looking at the fourth as well, would we
would you be okay with doing 9 to 11
again on the fourth? And it looks like
there is something at 11 that would be
nice if we didn't Yeah. have to
reschedule that. So yeah, 9 9 to
>> that works better for the department.
>> Um
>> cool.
>> All righty. Well, thank you guys all so
much for coming. Please send us your
public comment or any comments you have
about how this program should be
working. I really appreciate you all
taking the time to be here and spending
the first two hours of your day with us.
So, thank you guys all. so much.
>> Great. Thank you everyone.